A Guide to the Faculty Senate Minutes, 1969-2007: UA 0001
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Faculty Senate Minutes,
1969-2007
Special Collections, James Madison University
James Madison University Faculty Senate
UA 0001
1.0 cubic feet; 1 box
The Faculty Senate Minutes, 1969-2007, are comprised of minutes of the James Madison University Faculty Senate meetings.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
This collection was transferred to Special Collections in 1993 by the sitting Faculty Senate secretary.
Other Formats Available
Related audiocassette recordings of Faculty Senate meetings, 1979-1997, are not formally part of this collection and are catalogued as LD3141 .M56592 F34. These require reformatting prior to use.
Administrative History
The James Madison University Faculty Senate Committee completed a preliminary draft of a Faculty Senate Constitution in February 1972. The constitution with proposed suggestions were approved at the April 11, 1972 general faculty meeting. The Madison College Faculty Senate held its organization meeting in Blackwell Auditorium on May 23, 1972. The Faculty Senate held its inaugural meeting on September 9, 1972 in Harrison Hall.
As of 2018, the membership is comprised of one representative from each academic unit and one student representative. The JMU Faculty Senate's mission statement is as follows:
"The function of the Faculty Senate is to represent the faculty in the consideration of all policies that affect the academic climate and direction of the institution. The Faculty Senate seeks to create, maintain and protect a university environment conductive to the growth of scholarship, learning, teaching, research, service, and respect for human dignity and rights."
The Senate's responsibilities include:
Offering suggestions to the vice presidents for academic affairs and for administration and finance on matters of university organization, budget recommendations and revisions, facilities, planning, and mission at the university level
Consulting with appropriate resource persons concerning academic policy
Offering recommendations about admissions policies and enrollment management
Participating in university-wide curricular oversight through its representatives on the Committee on Academic Programs (CAP); and
Working with the Office of the Provost and Senior Vice President for Academic Affairs to maintain policies and procedures by which the faculty will be involved in the evaluation of academic administrators at the university level.
Scope and Content
The Faculty Senate Minutes, 1969-2007, are comprised chiefly of meeting minutes and memoranda produced by the JMU Faculty Senate.
The minutes begin with the first meeting of the Faculty Senate on September 9, 1972 and continue through 2007. Earlier materials related to the organization of the Senate include draft constitutions.
The subject matter of the minutes reflect and document the happenings in the Faculty Senate meetings. Topics include general announcements, enrollment numbers, salaries, reorganization and administrative changes, tenure and promotion, faculty handbook revisions, academic restructuring, and Faculty for Responsible Change (FRC). Additional materials include rosters, the Faculty Senate constitution, indices to minutes, and committee reports.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically with related materials filed after the meeting minutes.
Related Material
Office of the President: Faculty Minutes, 1909-1998, UA 0011, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA.
James Madison University Faculty Senate. [Meetings] [Sound recording]. Harrisonburg, VA: James Madison University, 1979-1997.
Bibliography
Faculty Senate of JMU. "About Faculty Senate." James Madison University. https://www.jmu.edu/facultysenate/about.shtml (accessed January 11, 2018).
Index Terms
Subjects:
Madison College -- History; Madison College -- Faculty; James Madison University -- History; James Madison University -- Faculty
Genre and Form Terms:
Minutes (administrative records); Rosters; Constitutions
- Minutes, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Minutes, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Minutes, 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Minutes, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Minutes, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Minutes, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Minutes, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Minutes, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Minutes, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Minutes, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Minutes, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Minutes, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Minutes, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Minutes, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Minutes, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Minutes, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Minutes, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Minutes, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Minutes, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Minutes, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Minutes, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Minutes, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Minutes, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Minutes, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Minutes, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Minutes, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Faculty Senate Indices to Minutes, 1972-1978, 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Faculty Senate Rosters, 1988-1995 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Faculty Committees, 1971-1979 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Faculty Senate Constitution, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Faculty Council, 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 31)